Guide to the Joseph H. Greenberg Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Joseph H. Greenberg papers
1961-2000
SC0615
Greenberg, Joseph H. (Joseph Harold), 1915-2001
40 Linear feet
Papers largely date from his tenure at Stanford and include correspondence, research notes and notebooks, course files, and reprints.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of the estate of Joseph Harold Greenberg, 2001.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Greenberg, a linguist who studied the origins of the world's languages, studied anthropology at Northwestern, receiving his Ph.D. in 1940. He taught at the University of Minnesota and Columbia before coming to Stanford in 1962. While at Stanford he was not only a professor of anthropology, but also helped to found the linguistics department and organized the African Studies Center in the 1960's. He died in 2001.
Description of the Collection
Papers largely date from his tenure at Stanford and include correspondence, research notes and notebooks, course files, and reprints.
Access Terms
Greenberg, Joseph H. (Joseph Harold), 1915-2001; Language and languages.; Linguistics.
Collection Contents
- Papers, Accession ARCH-2001-151
  *preliminary listing – still in process*
  - Notebooks & Notes
    - Eastern Sudanic (Southern Branch) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - [undetermined] (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Eastern Sudanic (Nubian) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - [undetermined] (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - [undetermined] (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - [undetermined] (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Central Sudanic (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - [undetermined] (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - [undetermined] (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - [undetermined] (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - West Atlantic (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Bantu Zone A (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - H. Rishereff- Research- African Linguistics (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - [undetermined] (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Macro Ge-languages (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Central (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - [undetermined] (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Central Saharan (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Gothric- Zone F, M, S, D (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Eastern Sudanic (Small Sub-Groups) (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Adamawa- Eastern (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Psycholinguistics (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Syllables 100 NS Study (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Psycholinguistics [1 of 2] (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Psycholinguistics [2 of 2] (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Experiment III: Psycholinguistics (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - NDFL-Summer 1969- Form letters Principal (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Word Comparison Lists [1 of 5] (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Word Comparison Lists [2 of 5] (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Word Comparison Lists [3 of 5] (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Word Comparison Lists [4 of 5] (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Word Comparison Lists [5 of 5] (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - History of Anthropology- Extra Notes (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - [Notes on Cariban languages and other topics] (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - [Notes & drafts for “Logical Bases of Linguistic Prescriptivism: A Parallel Between Classical Grammarians and Moslem Legal Theorists”; and possibly other materials] (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Log Book (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - New Guinea Vocabularies: II (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - III (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - History of Linguistics III (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - History of Linguistics- Notes [1 of 2] (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - History of Linguistics- Notes [2 of 2] (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Central Sudanic (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - [Kordopanian languages?] (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - General African (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Gloria Raspberry (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - unlabelled (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Guthrie- Zone E (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Mandingo (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Cross-River and Bantoid (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - “Wide” Bantu (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Bantu Noun Classes (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - unlabelled (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - unlabelled (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - unlabelled (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - unlabelled (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Area Studies- African Languages (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - [undetermined] (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - [undetermined] (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - [undetermined] (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - [undetermined] (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - [undetermined] (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Nigerian Studies (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - [undetermined] (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Noun Classes (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Language Survey of Ethiopia (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - [undetermined] (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Diary- Nigeria 1938 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - [undetermined] (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Linguistics and Biology (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Sino-Tibetan (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Notes [1 of 2] (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Notes [2 of 2] (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Regional Linguistic Notebooks- part 21 of 23- Siouan-Keresan-Iroquian (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Regional Linguistic Notebooks- part 18 of 23- Pentutian (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Tupian (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Guaycuru (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Arawakan (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - [undetermined] (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - [undetermined] (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - [undetermined] (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Regional Linguistic Notebooks- part 20 of 23- Oto-Mangue (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - [undetermined] (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - [undetermined] (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Algonkian-Wakashan (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - [undetermined] (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - [undetermined] (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Penutian Languages (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Andean Languages (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Macro-Carib (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - [undetermined] (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - [undetermined] (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Regional Linguistic Notebooks- part 16 of 23- Azteco-tanoan, Na-dene (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Arawak I (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - [undetermined] (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Regional Linguistic Notebooks- part 17 of 23- Na-dene Vocabularies (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Chibchan grammar (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Equatorial (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Tucanoan (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Macro-Chibchan (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Grammatical North American II (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Regional Linguistic Notebooks- part 19 of 23- Mexian-Penutian (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Regional Linguistic Notebooks- part 14 of 23- Tupi Proper (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Collective Numerics and Distributive (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Untitled [1 of 2] (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Untitled [2 of 2] (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Phonological Theory II (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Word Systems Notebook No. 1 [1 of 3] (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Word Systems Notebook No. 1 [2 of 3] (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Word Systems Notebook No. 1 [3 of 3] (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - [undetermined] (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - [undetermined] (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Quantification (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - [undetermined] (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - [undetermined] (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - [undetermined] (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - [undetermined] (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Regional Linguistic Notebooks- part 23 of 23- Algonkian-Wakashan (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Lateral Consonants in Mayan-Zoquean-Huave (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Regional Linguistic Notebooks-part 15 of 23- Chibchan (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Regional Linguistic Notebooks-part 12 of 23- Miscellaneous South American (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - [undetermined] (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Untitled [1 of 3] (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Untitled [2 of 3] (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Untitled [3 of 3] (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Tacana-Pano (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Ritwan-Mosan-Siouan-Caddo (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Na-dene Languages (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Gur (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - G. K. Moble Notebook (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - [undetermined] (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - [undetermined] (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - [undetermined] (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - LSA address [1 of 2] (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - LSA address [2 of 2] (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Linguistic analysis [1 of 2] (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Linguistic analysis [2 of 2] (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Possessive Constructions (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Word Accentual Systems [1 of 3] (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Word Accentual Systems [2 of 3] (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Word Accentual Systems [3 of 3] (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Tonogenesis Notes [1 of 2] (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Tonogenesis Notes [2 of 2] (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - [undetermined] (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - [undetermined] (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - [undetermined] (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Diachronic Factors in Phonological Theory (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Indo-European Substantive Distension (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Untitled [1 of 2] (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Untitled [2 of 2] (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Universal Methodology (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - [undetermined] (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Numerals- 1976 Linguistic Institute (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Language Universals (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Notebook G2 [1 of 2] (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Notebook G2 [2 of 2] (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Peoples of Africa (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Class Notes: History of Anthropological Theory 1981 [1 of 4] (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Class Notes: History of Anthropological Theory 1981 [2 of 4] (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Class Notes: History of Anthropological Theory 1981 [3 of 4] (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Class Notes: History of Anthropological Theory 1981 [4 of 4] (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Notes for Course on Historical Linguistics (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Notes for Language, Culture and Society (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Typology and Universals: Class Notes [1 of 4] (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Typology and Universals: Class Notes [2 of 4] (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - Typology and Universals: Class Notes [3 of 4] (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Typology and Universals: Class Notes [4 of 4] (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - KAJE (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - [undetermined] (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - [undetermined] (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - Plateau Languages (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - Ginoiri (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - Irigwe (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - Tera (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - [undetermined] (Box 6, Folder 39)
    - [undetermined] (Box 6, Folder 40)
    - Anthropology 174 / Linguistics 202 [1 of 4] (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Anthropology 174 / Linguistics 202 [2 of 4] (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Anthropology 174 / Linguistics 202 [3 of 4] (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Anthropology 174 / Linguistics 202 [4 of 4] (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - [undetermined] (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Contemporary Theory (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Language Families of Africa (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Historical Linguistics Course [1 of 3] (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Historical Linguistics Course [2 of 3] (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Historical Linguistics Course [3 of 3] (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - [undetermined] (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Untitled [1 of 4] (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Untitled [2 of 4] (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Untitled [3 of 4] (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Untitled [4 of 4] (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Class notes-Typology and Universals [1 of 3] (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Class notes-Typology and Universals [2 of 3] (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Class notes-Typology and Universals [3 of 3] (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Course Notes, Linguistics 205 (1985) [1 of 2] (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Course Notes, Linguistics 205 (1985) [2 of 2] (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - History of Anthropology Notebook (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - [undetermined] (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Bola Tangale (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - BUJI (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - IRIGWE notes (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Ninzam (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Nungu (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Fizere (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - Diryanchi (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - Mbarike (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - Niger Congo Noun class affixes (Box 7, Folder 31)
    - Linguistic evidence regarding Bantu origins [1 of 2] (Box 7, Folder 32)
    - Linguistic evidence regarding Bantu origins [2 of 2] (Box 7, Folder 33)
    - Areal Characteristics of African languages [1 of 2] (Box 7, Folder 34)
    - Areal Characteristics of African languages [2 of 2] (Box 7, Folder 35)
    - The last stages of grammatical elements. Degrammaticalization & Regrammaticalization [1 of 2] (Box 7, Folder 36)
    - The last stages of grammatical elements. Degrammaticalization & Regrammaticalization [2 of 2] (Box 7, Folder 37)
    - Language and Nationalism (Box 7, Folder 38)
    - Kinship terminology [1 of 2] (Box 7, Folder 39)
    - Kinship terminology [2 of 2] (Box 7, Folder 40)
    - Indo-Pacific (Box 7, Folder 41)
    - Initial Consonant Mutation (Box 7, Folder 42)
    - Marked and Unmarked Categories (Box 7, Folder 43)
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence A – I, 1963-2000 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence J – S, 1961-2000 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence T – Z and unsorted, 1970-2000 (Box 3)
  - Details on unprocessed boxes
    - Courses/Lectures (Box 18b)
    - Courses/Lectures (Box 19)
    - Courses/Lectures (Box 20)
    - Courses/Lectures (Box 21)
    - Courses/Lectures (Box 22)
    - Research notes and notebooks (Box 24)
    - Notes for essays in linguistics (1) (Box 25b, Folder 1)
    - Notes for essays in linguistics (2) (Box 25b, Folder 2)
    - Notes for essays in linguistics (3) (Box 25b, Folder 3)
    - Relative pronoun and P.I.E. (1) (Box 25b, Folder 4)
    - Relative pronoun and P.I.E. (2) (Box 25b, Folder 5)
    - Rethinking linguistics diachronically, 1977-78 (Box 25b, Folder 6)
    - Numerals (1) (Box 25b, Folder 7)
    - Numerals (2) (Box 25b, Folder 8)
    - Russian research on universals (Box 25b, Folder 9)
    - Notes on structural syllable (Box 25b, Folder 10)
    - Psycholinguists (1) (Box 25b, Folder 11)
    - Psycholinguists (2) (Box 25b, Folder 12)
    - Seven theories (1) (Box 25b, Folder 13)
    - Seven theories (2) (Box 25b, Folder 14)
    - Seven theories (3) (Box 25b, Folder 15)
    - Vowel paper – text and notes (Box 25b, Folder 16)
    - Vowel articles – manuscript (Box 25b, Folder 17)
    - Reviews of Greenberg's works (Box 25b, Folder 18)
    - Language in the Americas – Greenberg's reply to reviewers (Box 25b, Folder 19)
    - Language in the Americas – reviews of (Box 25b, Folder 20)
    - Reviews by Greenberg 1940s (Box 25b, Folder 21)
    - Reviews by Greenberg 1950s (Box 25b, Folder 22)
    - Reviews by Greenberg 1960s (Box 25b, Folder 23)
    - Review by Greenberg: Language and Archaeology 1988 (Box 25b, Folder 24)
    - Reviews by Greenberg 1990s (Box 25b, Folder 25)
    - Greenberg, "Are there mixed languages?" (Box 25b, Folder 26)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 25b, Folder 27)
    - Survey form and form letter re African music and oral data (Box 25b, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence 2000 (Box 25b, Folder 29)
    - Correspondence 2000 (Box 25b, Folder 30)
    - Audio tapes:
      - Dicos totonas (reel) (Box 25b)
      - Compadres & comadres marriage customs (reel) (Box 25b)
      - Juan Castaneda – Santiago – Taide #103 (reel) (Box 25b)
      - Juan Castaneda stories (second time) #101 (reel) (Box 25b)
      - Beliefs [possibly blank] (reel) (Box 25b)
      - Assorted audio cassettes, mostly unlabeled (Box 25b)
    - Research notes and notebooks (Box 27)
    - Research notes and notebooks (Box 28)
- Papers, Accession ARCH-2002-110
  - Certificates (in oversized box, but not all are oversized):
    - New York Academy of Sciences, Dec. 3, 1980 (Box 1 os)
    - Distinguished Contribution to African Studies [Stanford] (Box 1 os)
    - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1973 (Box 1 os)
    - Linguistic Society of America (Box 1 os)
    - American Anthropological Association, Distinguished Lecturer 1970 (Box 1 os)
    - American Philosophical Society 1975 (Box 1 os)
    - Haile Selassie Award, 1967 (Box 1 os)
    - National Academy of Sciences 1965 (Box 1 os)
- Papers, Accession ARCH-2004-309
  - Bibliography (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical articles, obituaries, etc. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Interviews: "Interview with Dr. J. H. & Mrs. S. Greenberg," The Piltdown Newsletter, Winter/Spring 1973; transcript of interviews between Ansar Dill and Joseph H. Greenberg for the introduction to Selected Writings of Joseph H. Greenberg (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Photographs (1 of Greenberg on the Gutenberg express bus 1984, 1 of papers on display) (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Papers, Accesion ARCH-2008-257
  - Interview of Joseph Greenberg by John Rawlings, 2001 – audiocassette and transcript (Box 1)
General note
Collection is unprocessed; please consult the University Archivist for access.